<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Canterburies crueltie covvorking vvith his prelaticall brethren, in the persecuting of Peter Smart, and other godly Protestants, for withstanding their superstitious proceedings in the bringing of innovation into the church. With their insulting treachery secretly wrought against his Majesty, our religion, lives, and liberties. Humbly presented to the consideration of the right honorable the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled By Peter Smart.</title>
            <author>Smart, Peter, 1569-1652?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60397</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835803</idno>
  <idno type="VID">25</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240889323</idno>
  <idno type="STC">Wing S4014A</idno>
  <idno type="STC">Wing S4012</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 22639</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC R12970</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99835803e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60397)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1035:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Canterburies crueltie covvorking vvith his prelaticall brethren, in the persecuting of Peter Smart, and other godly Protestants, for withstanding their superstitious proceedings in the bringing of innovation into the church. With their insulting treachery secretly wrought against his Majesty, our religion, lives, and liberties. Humbly presented to the consideration of the right honorable the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled By Peter Smart.</title>
                  <author>Smart, Peter, 1569-1652?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 59 [i.e. 39], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed, 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Novemb. 3. 1640. To the honourable, the knights, citizens, and burgesses of the Commons House of Parliament, the humble petition of Peter Smart, a poore prisoner in the Kings Bench" (caption title, STC 22639, Wing S4014A) begins pagination on B1r. "Finis" on p. 16; the item continues with documents relating to the case.</note>
                  <note>P. 39 misnumbered 59.</note>
                  <note>Probably issued with "A short treatise of altars, altar-furniture, altar-cringing, and musick of all the quire" (Wing S4014).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library ("Early English books, 1475-1640", reel 1035, and "Early English books, 1641-1700" reels 1035 and 2135.</note>
                  <note>"Early English books, 1475-1640" reel 1035: lacking all after p. 16; "Early English books, 1641-1700" reel 2135: lacking all except Peter Smart's petition and related documents.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cosin, John, 1594-1672.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England. --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 3. 1640.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>To the Honourable, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgesses of the Commons House of PARLIAMENT, The humble Petition of <hi>Peter Smart,</hi> a poore prisoner in the Kings Bench,</head>
            <p>Humbly sheweth,</p>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat after the death of Bishop <hi>James,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop <hi>Neale</hi> coming to the See of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the then Deane and Prebendaries of that Cathedrall Church cast the Communion-Table out of the same Church, and erected an high Altar at the East end of the Quire, of Marble stones, with a carved screen most gloriously painted and guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which cost about two hundred pound.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And they bought for forty shillings one Cope found in a search for Masse-Priests, embroydered with the image of the Trinity, and other Images; and another Cope which cost about ten groats, which had beene a long time used by the Youth of <hi>Durham</hi> in their Sports and May-games: a very
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25:2"/>fooles coat, both which Copes they used at the Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Communion at their Altar.</p>
            <p n="3">3 To which Altar themselves both did, and forced others to use most unreasonable frequent bowing.</p>
            <p n="4">4 D. <hi>Cosin</hi> officiated thereat with his face toward the East, and back toward the people.</p>
            <p n="5">5 They (the Deane and Prebendaries) did likewise take away the Morning Prayer, to which about two hundred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons did usually resort, used for the space of about sixty yeares in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> as in all other Cathedrall and Collegiate Churches in <hi>England,</hi> to be read at six a clock plainly and distinctly in a peculiar place appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for that purpose by Commissioners under the great Seale of <hi>England, Septemb.</hi> 25. <hi>primo Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 And instead thereof altered the same into singing with Instruments, without reading any Chapters or Psalmes at the ordinary ten a clock Prayer.</p>
            <p n="7">7 They did likewise set up fifty three glorious Images and pictures over the Bishops Throne, and about the Quire in the said Church.</p>
            <p n="8">8 And they burnt two hundred waxe candles in one Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlemas night in honour of our Lady.</p>
            <p n="9">9 They brought in sundry other superstitious and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable observations into that Church.</p>
            <p n="10">10 To the observation whereof they forced divers, and publikely brawled in the time of Divine Service in the Church with others, who would not observe the same; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them lazie sowes, and dirty whores, tearing some gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomens apparell; calling them Pagans, and thrusting them out of the Church, who refused to obey them therein: for which violent, turbulent demeanour D. <hi>Cosin</hi> was twice indicted at the Quarter-Sessions holden at <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25:2"/> 11 Some of them preached in a Cope and sate to heare Divine Service in a Cope in the said Cathedrall Church.</p>
            <p n="12">12 And others of them, <hi>viz.</hi> D. <hi>Cosin,</hi> preaching in the said Church upon the Parable of the tares; delivered this doctrine, <hi>That the reformers of the Church, when they tooke away the Masse, took away or mar'd all Religion, and the whole Service of God;</hi> And <hi>that it was a deformation indeed, though they called it a reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 And he, the said D. <hi>Cosin,</hi> publikely maintained, <hi>that the Kings Majesty is not supreme Head of the Church in England, nor could be so called, for that he had no more power to meddle in Ecclesiasticall matters then the fellow that rubs his horses heeles;</hi> for which he was indicted <hi>Anno</hi> 1629. at the Assizes at <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and found guilty thereof by the oathes of three men of worth: which indictment remaines yet untraversed.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Your Petitioner being a senior Prebendary of that Church, and one of His Majesties High Commissioners for Causes Ecclesiasticall in the Province of <hi>York,</hi> and in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice punctually conformable to the Doctrine and Discipline established in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the same innovations, and doctrines, according to his place and calling.</p>
            <p n="15">15 But not prevailing therein, he in July 27. 1628. accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the third Injunction, preached in the said Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the said Innovations; for which Sermon he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently convented before the High-Commission holden at <hi>Durham,</hi> and before any Articles exhibited against him, suspended, and his living sequestred. And after his answer upon oath to the Articles, and sixe moneths detention in the said High-Commission, where he was proceeded against with all rigour and extremity, according to the expresse command
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25:3"/>(as some of the High Commissioners in open Court said) of some Bishops in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 He was served with a Warrant under the High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission Seale for the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and hands of <hi>William</hi> L. Bishop of <hi>London, Samuel</hi> L. Bishop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> D. <hi>Caesar,</hi> and D. <hi>Sammes,</hi> to appeare before the High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission holden at <hi>London,</hi> and there forced againe to take his Oath <hi>Ex Officio,</hi> and to attend above a quarter of a yeere for Articles, which were pretended to be matters of high nature against him.</p>
            <p n="17">17 And was afterward remanded without any Articles to <hi>Yorke,</hi> where in August 1630. they proceeded to sentence <hi>ex parte,</hi> having denied your Petitioner a Commission to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine witnesses on his behalfe: where he was excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, degraded, fined seven hundred pound, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned, for opposing and preaching against the said Doctrines and superstitious Innovations.</p>
            <p n="81">81 Notwithstanding that, D. <hi>Cosin,</hi> and one M. <hi>Burgoyne</hi> were indicted in August, 1629. at <hi>Durham</hi> Assizes upon se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Bills, and found guilty thereof, which remaine like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise untraversed; this legall conviction notwithstanding, the said D. <hi>Cosin</hi> since is made one of His Majesties Chaplains in Ordinary, admitted to his Degree of Doctor, Master of <hi>Peter-House</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Vice-Chancellour of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> also Dean of <hi>Peterborough</hi> (beside foure great livings he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) and all proceedings upon the former indictments against him stopped.</p>
            <p n="19">19 That your Petitioner was two severall times impriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at <hi>York</hi> before their said sentence, for which injurious imprisonment he commenced his action at law against some of the said high Commissioners, and obtained Judgment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25:3"/>thereupon, and sixe hundred pound dammages, yet cannot have any fruit thereof.</p>
            <p n="20">20 That your Petitioner petitioned, and preferred Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles into the High Commission in <hi>London</hi> against the said Dean and Prebendaries for the said Doctrines, and Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, profering to give good security to prove all the said Articles: But the said Petition and Articles were utterly reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the said Court, who said, they would not suffer such worthy men to be questioned.</p>
            <p n="21">21 That your Petitioner hath been kept in prison upon the said sentence in great penury and want almost ten yeares, and lost both his dignity, and Parsonage, and whole estate, whereby he, his wife and children are utterly ruined in their persons, posterity, and fortunes.</p>
            <p n="22">22 That your Petitioner is now, and hath been above twelve moneths close prisoner, and His Majesties most gracious Reference in his behalfe unto the now Lord Bishop of <hi>Durham</hi> revoked; upon pretence that he was lately at <hi>Glascow</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> preaching and instigating the Scots a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Episcopall government; whereas he was never at <hi>Glas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow</hi> in his life, nor in <hi>Scotland</hi> these twenty four years past: nor had directly nor indirectly any intelligence with the Scots.</p>
            <p n="23">23 In tender commiseration whereof, your Petitioner most humbly beseecheth your serious consideration, both of his miserable distressed condition, and great opressions: as also of the said Innovations and offences of the said D. <hi>Cosin,</hi> and the other Prebendaries of <hi>Durham,</hi> with their abettors, who persecuted and censured your Petitioner: And to take such course, both for your poore Petitioners releife and release; As also for reformation of the said Doctrines, Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, and proceedings, and prevention of the like hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as to your great wisdomes shall seeme meet.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:25:4"/>
            <p> And for that your Petitioner is much decayed in his health, by reason of his late restraint, and very poore: he humbly beseecheth you presently to give order for his release from his close imprisonment; and that he may have present Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the said Judgment for the said sixe hundred pounds, whereby he shall be enabled to prosecute and prove this his most just complaint against all his adversaries. And your Petitioner shall pray, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>A Speech made before the Lords by <hi>M. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Rous</hi> Esquire, March <hi>16. 1640.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Against D. COSIN, and many others impeached by the House of Commons in <hi>M. Smarts</hi> Cause.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am commanded by the House of Commons, to present to your Lordships a Declaration and impeachment against D. <hi>Cosin</hi> and others, upon the complaint of <hi>M. Peter Smart,</hi> which <hi>M. Smart</hi> was a Protomartyr, or first Confessour of note in the last dayes of persecution.</p>
            <p>The whole matter is a tree, whereof the branches and fruit are manifest in the Articles of this Declaration, which being read, I shall (with your Lordships favour) discover and lay open the root.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Declaration was read, consisting of eighteen Articles delivered to the Lords in writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:25:4"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="declaration">
                        <head>
                           <hi>The Commons Declaration and Impeachment upon the Complaint of</hi> Peter Smart <hi>Clerk, late Prebendary of</hi> Durham, <hi>against</hi> Iohn Cosin, <hi>Doctor in Divinity,</hi> Ferdinando Morecroft, George Morecroft, William Iames, Iohn Robson, Gabriel Clerke, Eleazer Duncum, <hi>and</hi> Thomas Carre, <hi>Prebendaries of</hi> Durham: <hi>and against</hi> William Lawd <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>Sir</hi> Charles Caesar, <hi>Sir</hi> Iohn Lamb, William Sammes, Edmund Pope, <hi>D.</hi> Aylott, <hi>High Commissioners of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of</hi> Canterbury: <hi>and against</hi> Iohn Scott <hi>Dean of</hi> Yorke, Phinees Hodshon, Henry Wickham, George Stanhope, <hi>Prebendaries of</hi> Yorke, <hi>Sir</hi> George Radcliffe, William Easdall, Iohn Bramhall <hi>now Bishop of</hi> Derry <hi>in</hi> Ireland, Richard Perrott, Edmund Kay, Richard Marsh, Timothy Thriscrosse, Robert Faucon, Henry Thriscrosse, Iohn Lively, Tho. Burwell, <hi>High Commissioners of the Province of</hi> Yorke, <hi>and</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Blanchard, <hi>Pursevant to the said High-Commission, and against Sir</hi> Francis Windebanke, <hi>for severall crimes and misdemeanours.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head>The Impeachment.</head>
                        <p n="1">1 THat after the death of D. <hi>James</hi> late Bishop of <hi>Durham,</hi> D. <hi>Neale</hi> succeeding him in that Bishoprick, during the time he was Bishop, the said D. <hi>Cosin, Ferd. Morecroft, George Morecroft, William James, John Robson, Gabriel Clerk,</hi> together with <hi>Richard Hunt</hi> late Deane, and others late Prebendaries of <hi>Durham,</hi> took away the Communion Table of that Cathedrall Church, and erected an Altar of Marble stones set upon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns, with many Cherubims thereupon, and a carved screen cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously painted and guilded set over the same. Which Altar, Copes, Organs, Images, Pictures, with other furniture, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull alterations in the said Church cost the said Deane and Chapter above two thousand pound.</p>
                        <p>To which Altar thus set up were frequent bowing, which bowing did increase after D. <hi>Cosin</hi> came to be Prebend there, few going or coming into the said Church without low obeysance:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25:5"/>and D. <hi>Cosin</hi> did officiate at the said Altar with his face toward the East, and back toward the people, at the time of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of the holy Communion.</p>
                        <p n="2">2 That the said Dean and Prebendaries bought one Cope found in a search for Masse-Priests, whereupon was imbroydered the image of the Trinity: <hi>viz.</hi> an old mans face, a crucifix, and a dove; and other two Copes, one having a crucifix upon it, which because they were short, they cut and made into one, whereby the crucifix fell upon the hinder part of him that bare it. And another Cope which cost about two hundred pound, which Copes they frequently used at the Administration of the holy Communion at the said Altar, some of them preaching in a Cope, and sitting to hear Service in a Cope in the said Church.</p>
                        <p n="3">3 That the said Deane and Prebendaries did also bring in and practice in the said Church sundry innovations in divine Service, both in time, place and manner, changing the Morning Prayer, to which about two hundred persons usually resorted, used for the space of sixty yeares in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> to be read at six a clock plainly and distinctly in a peculiar place appointed for that purpose by Commissioners under the great Seal of <hi>England, Septemb.</hi> 25. <hi>primo Eliz.</hi> into solemne Service and singing, both instrumentall and vocall, whereby it was brought into so late an houre, that some who formerly frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the old Morning Prayer, could not attend this. And Judge <hi>Hutton</hi> in particular complained, that the longnesse and latenesse of it was inconsistent with publike imployments. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they took the old Morning Prayer quite away for divers yeares, and instead thereof divided the ordinary Morning Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, making two of one, whereby there were neither Chapters nor Psalmes read at ten a clock Prayer.</p>
                        <p n="4">4 That the said Dean and Prebendaries set up and renewed many gorgeous images and pictures, three whereof were statues
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25:5"/>of stone, one of which standing in the middest, represented the picture of Christ, with a golden beard, a blew cap, and Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayes upon his head.</p>
                        <p n="5">5 That the said Dean and Prebendaries did use an excessive number of candles: more upon a Saints day, then upon the Lords day; And caused the same candles to be lighted in the said Church, in a new, strange and superstitious manner, burning two hundred wax candles in one Candlemas night, whereof there were about sixty upon and about the Altar, where there was no use of light, nor Service then said: whereupon a Popish Priest spake, let us Papists resort to the said Church, to see how D. <hi>Cosin,</hi> and the Prebendaries of <hi>Durham</hi> doe play our apes. D. <hi>Cosin</hi> set up some of these candles himself, and caused others with ladders to set up more round about the Quire, some of which the said Dean sent his servant to take down; but D. <hi>Cosin</hi> did struggle with him in time of prayer, to the great disturbance of the congregation: the manner of lighting the candles was this; they caused two Choristers, in their Surplices to come from the West end of the Quire, with lighted torches in their hands, who after sundry bowings by the way, to and at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, did light the candles upon the same with their torches: which done, they returned backward with many bowings, their faces toward the Altar, till they came to the Quire doore: which ceremony of lighting the excessive number of candles came into the said Church after D. <hi>Cosin</hi> was Prebendary.</p>
                        <p n="6">6 That the said Dean and Prebendaries did absolutely forbid and prohibit the Psalms in Meeter to be sung before and after Sermon, and at the Administration of the holy Communion: and instead thereof turned prayers and peeces of reading Psalmes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Anthems and caused them to be sung, so that the people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood not whether they were prayers or no. Whereupon D. <hi>Cosin</hi> observing that they kneeled not, sent Vergerers to some to command them, and spake to others himself, saying, <hi>Masters you must kneele, it is a prayer, you must kneele.</hi> And they caused
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25:6"/>an Anthem to be sung which was not the Word of God; as namely the three Kings of <hi>Cullen: Jaspar, Melchior,</hi> and <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar,</hi> and caused the Organs to play, and the whole Quire to sing, at the Administration of both the Sacraments; to the great disturbance of those holy Actions.</p>
                        <p n="7">7 That the said Deane and Prebendaries caused many pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and carved Images (besides those that were in the said Church) to be set upon the Font, amongst which was a Dove carved, and the foure Evangelists, and <hi>John</hi> baptizing <hi>Christ</hi> in <hi>Iordan</hi> painted; which did appeare at the opening of the Font: which Font they caused to be removed from the ancient usuall place in the Quire, where it formerly stood; and placed it out of the Quire, where divine Service is never read.</p>
                        <p n="8">8 That the said Dean and Prebendaries did cause a knife to be kept in the Vestrey for cutting of the Sacramentall bread, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing appropriated only for that use: And was commonly called, knowne, and shewed to those who came to see the gay ornaments of the Church, by the name of the consecrated knife. And D. <hi>Cosin</hi> did consecrate the cushions and forms by crossing them, before the people came to the Communion.</p>
                        <p n="9">9 That the said Dean and Prebendaries did imploy a Painter, and Glasier (profest Papists) to serve the said Cathedrall Church in their severall uses: and brought in, and practised in the said Church severall other superstitious Innovations tending to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</p>
                        <p n="10">10 That D. <hi>Cosin</hi> preaching in the said Church upon the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the tares, said, <hi>That the reformers of our Church, when they tooke away the Masse, tooke away or mar'd all religion, and the whole service of God: they called it a reformation, but it was indeed a defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation:</hi> And that the Masse was not so taken away, but that the presence of Christ still remaineth; and that if the reformation were otherwise, it were not a reformed but a deformed religion. And that he meant of a corporall presence was plain, for that he complained afterward in the said Sermon, that some had thrust
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25:6"/>out the presence of Christ: and he likewise said, that in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time when Popery was put out, the reformation was a deformation, and instead of bringing in order, they brought in ordure.</p>
                        <p n="11">11 That D. <hi>Cosin</hi> perswading a Papist to come to Church, said, that the Body of Christ was substantially and really in the Sacrament: and shewing him the new Service-Book intended for <hi>Scotland,</hi> he said, it was all one with theirs of the Romish Church, for there was in it, the <hi>Introit,</hi> the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle, Gospel, Offertory, Canon, Consecration, Communion</hi> &amp; <hi>Post-Communion.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="12">12 That D. <hi>Cosin</hi> at a publike dinner said, <hi>That the King was not su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head of the Church in England, nor could be so called;</hi> for which, and introducing and practising of severall the said Ceremonies, he was indicted at the general Assizes in <hi>Durham,</hi> 1629. and <hi>Billa vera</hi> returned, &amp; spoke other scandalous, scornfull and malicious words against His Majesties supremacy.</p>
                        <p n="13">13 That these innovations in the Communion-Table, Font, Candles, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, Images, Copes, Singing, Vestments, Gestures, Prayers, Doctrines, and speeches of the said <hi>Cosin;</hi> &amp; the other alterations being unlawfully introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, &amp; practised in the said Cathedrall Church by the said Dean &amp; Prebends, <hi>Peter Smart</hi> one of the Prebends aforesaid, opposed the same, and in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his duty, place and calling did upon July 27. 1628. being the Lords day, preach in the said Church against the same, reproving these innovations, &amp; innovators, &amp; exhorted the people to keep themselves from the infections of them, in which Sermon there was nothing scandalous, nor disagreeable to the Word of God, the Doctrine and Discipline of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="14">14 That notwithstanding the said D. <hi>Cosin,</hi> both upon M. <hi>Smarts</hi> read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Text, and going on in his Sermon suitable thereunto: very turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently demeaned himselfe in the said Church; and the Sermon being ended, M. <hi>Smarts</hi> troubles began, for there was not one day set betweene his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and his punishment, for the said D. <hi>Cosin</hi> and <hi>William Iames,</hi> together with others since deceased, the same Lords day did send a Warrant in the nature of an Attatchment, under the high-Commission seale for that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, by two Pursevants, to convent him before them: whereupon he personally appeared, and delivered to them the imperfect notes of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which were sealed up, and he ordered to attend the next day, that the same might be truly copied out as he preached them, and as he should deliver them upon oath, and be bound in a Recognizance of 100. pound to appeare before them upon a days warning: but the said Dean and Prebendaries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their order, did break up the seales, and wrote out severall copies of the imperfect notes, and sent them to <hi>London</hi> to severall Bishops. And the same day D. <hi>Cosin</hi> asked the advice of a Counsellour, whether he might not break open M. <hi>Smarts</hi> doors to search for papers, adding this reason, because
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25:7"/>the Lords of the Counsell did so. And afterward the said Dean and Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries, with <hi>Iohn Lively</hi> and <hi>D. Easdell,</hi> were informers, prosecutors and Judges for six moneths against the said <hi>Peter Smart</hi> at <hi>Durham</hi> for the same, where they censured him by two Acts of Sequestration, and one of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spension, and kept him <hi>ex officio</hi> in continuall personal attendance under great bonds, and paines of excommunication about foure moneths before there were any Articles exhibited against him; and five moneths before any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor was allowed him, and after he had there answered Articles upon oath, and six moneths detention before them; they caused a Warrant under the High-Commission Seal for the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and hands of <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Lawd</hi> Bishop of <hi>London, Samuel Harsnet</hi> Bishop of <hi>Norwich, D. Caesar</hi> and <hi>D. Sammes,</hi> to be served upon him for his appearance at <hi>London;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward by Act in Court unlawfully transmitted him to <hi>London,</hi> to answer in the High Commission there for the same cause.</p>
                        <p>That the 12. of February 1628. M. <hi>Smart</hi> appearing at <hi>London</hi> before <hi>William</hi> then Bishop of <hi>London,</hi> now Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Lamb, Edm. Pope, W. Sammes</hi> and D. <hi>Aleif,</hi> together with others deceased, they forced him to take the oath <hi>ex officio</hi> again, to answer Articles, which the said Archbishop said were matters of high nature against him, and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to be examined thereupon before his departure out of <hi>London;</hi> and to be proceeded against <hi>ex officio,</hi> because the said Dean and Prebendaries had recommended the cause thither: according to which order <hi>M. Smart</hi> atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded severall times upon the Register of the said High-Commission to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, but could never get any Articles. And the said 23. of Aprill 1629. the said Archbishop, Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi> and others did transmit him and the cause, with all the letters and complaints of the said Dean and Prebendaries against him unto <hi>Yorke</hi> unto the High-Commission there without any allowance of charges for his unjust vexation at <hi>London;</hi> because he was convented thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and proceeded against upon complaint of the said Dean and Prebenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and refused to admit of M. <hi>Smarts</hi> Articles against them, although he offered sufficient bond of a thousand pound to prove the same, saying, they would not suffer such worthy men to be questioned.</p>
                        <p n="15">15. That the 20 of June, <hi>Samuel</hi> then Arch-Bishop of <hi>York,</hi> Doctor <hi>Hodgson,</hi> and others, sent a Warrant under the High-Commission Seale for that Province, to convent him before them at <hi>York:</hi> And upon his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance forced him to take the Oath <hi>ex Officio</hi> to answer Articles, and afterward unlawfully fined him five hundred pound by intimation, and certified the same into the Exchequer, and in November following com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him unlawfully to prison, and in December, committed him againe, and forced him again to take a fourth oath <hi>ex Officio,</hi> to answer Articles Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionalls,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25:7"/>and continued him in vexatious attendance before them under great bonds untill the third of August 1630. when they proceeded to sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <hi>ex parte:</hi> having sundry times before denyed him a commission to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine witnesses on his behalfe, interrupted his counsell, and suffered not the Breef of his defence to be read; And made many bitter invective speeches against him, and decreed that he should make a Recantation, <hi>conceptis verbis,</hi> as it should be delivered to him in three severall places, in <hi>York,</hi> and <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> to be suspended totally <hi>ab officio,</hi> fined 400 pound, condemned in costs of suit, and committed to prison.</p>
                        <p n="16">16 That the second of September following, they excommunicated him, November the 10 sequestred all his Ecclesiasticall livings, and Novemb. 18. they degraded him, <hi>ab omni gradu &amp; dignitate clericali,</hi> because he did not recant, and pay costs: by colour of which degradation, his Prebendship, which Doctor <hi>Carre</hi> hath most injuriously ever since injoyed, and Parson<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age were both taken from him, and he ever since hath been kept in prison, and layen under all the said severall censures, and indured divers other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conscionable, and unjust Acts and proceedings, both at <hi>Durham, London,</hi> and <hi>York;</hi> By which heavy and unjust oppressions, his life hath been severall times evidently endangered, and he and his children, lost and spent above 14000 pound of reall estate, whereby they are utterly undone.</p>
                        <p n="17">17 That M. <hi>Smart Pasch.</hi> 5. <hi>Car. Reg.</hi> brought an action of false im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment in the Kings Bench, against D. <hi>Hodgson,</hi> D. <hi>Easdall,</hi> and <hi>Roger Blanchard</hi> their Pursevant, for their said two unjust commitments before their sentence, and after seven Termes spent in delayes, and severall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory orders for them to plead, he obtained judgment upon a <hi>nihil dicit,</hi> and 600 pound damages upon a writ of Enquiry, which was returned into the said Court; And by the then Judges over-ruled, and M. <hi>Smart</hi> ordered to accept a long and frivolous plea contrary to the opinion of Judge <hi>Crook;</hi> to which plea he demurred, but could not get it argued, whereby he never received any benefit or profit thereof.</p>
                        <p n="18">18 That in July 1638 M. <hi>Smart</hi> having obtained his Majesties most gracious reference in his behalf, unto the now Bishop of <hi>Durham,</hi> Secretary <hi>Windebank</hi> did revoke the same, by his Letter to the said <hi>Bishop;</hi> who upon receipt thereof, sent two Pursevants with a warrant under the High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission seal for that Province, signed by himself, <hi>Thomas Burwell,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; whereby he was apprehended, and caried prisoner unto <hi>Durham,</hi> where he remained prisoner above six weekes: And from thence brought him prisoner in a cart to <hi>London,</hi> to the said Secretary, who remanded him prisoner to the Kings Bench; and about two dayes after, by the said Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries command was taken out of his own chamber, and put into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25:8"/>prison, where he remained about a moneth, and sixteen weekes more close prisoner, in his own chamber, upon pretence that he had been at <hi>Glas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> preaching and instigating the Scotts against Episcopall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: whereas he was never in <hi>Glascow</hi> in his life, nor had directly nor indirectly any intelligence with the Scots. Vpon which his said imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he severall times petitioned the said Secretary, Lord Bishop, Arch-Bishop, and his Majesty, but could never get any release or examination thereof; All which he hath, and is still ready to prove; by which unjust, cruell, and illegall Acts, and proceedings, of the said Bishop, Dean and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Durham,</hi> and the said high Commission of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> religion hath been mightily scandalized, the Church polluted, Iustice perverted, the lawes Ecclesiasticall and Temporall, and the lawfull liberty of the Subjects of this kingdome violated and infringed: And the said <hi>Peter Smart,</hi> his wife children and family most unjustly and unchristianly undone, and ruined, to the great dishonour of God, maintenance of injustice, and pernicious example to posterity.</p>
                        <p>All which said matters and things, the Commons do transmit to your Lordships; and impeach all the said partyes delinquent, to the end that they may be called to answer their severall crimes, and receive such condigne punishment: And M. <hi>Smart</hi> such reparations joyntly and severally from them all both for the said losses, and also for his dammage here by sustained, and that he be restored to his Eccesiasticall dignity, and living: and all the said sentences, and proceedings may be declared to be illegall, and unjust. And that such further proceedings, examinations, tryalls and judgments be upon every of them had, and used, as is agreeable to law and Justice.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>As soon as this Declaration was read to the Lords, <hi>M. Rous</hi> proceeded thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am now to discover the root of <hi>M. Smarts</hi> persecution: Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships have heard of a great designe to bring in Popery: you have heard of armies of souldiers, and particularly of the Popish Irish Army, the burden and complaint of the Commons: but there is another Army not so much spoken of, and that is an Army of Priests: for since Altars came in (so they delight to be called) it is a saying of <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, that when Antichrist is come, <hi>Praeparatus est exercitus Sacerdotum,</hi> there is an Army of Priests ready to receive him: this is fulfilled in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25:8"/>our time, for certainly this Army of Priests doth many wayes advance the designe and plot of Popery.</p>
            <p>A first is, by the subversion of our laws and government: our Laws and Popery cannot stand together, but either Popery must overthrow our Lawes, or our Lawes must overthrow Popery: but to overthrow our Lawes, they must overthrow Parliaments: and to overthrow Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they must overthrow property: they must bring the Subjects goods to be arbitrarily disposed, that so there may be no need of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. This hath been done by <hi>D. Manwaring</hi> (whom we finde wanting yet not in the seats, but at the Barre of the Lords House) and the like by <hi>D. Beale,</hi> and I think it was the intent of the late Canons.</p>
            <p>A second way, by which this Army of Priests advanceth this Popish designe, is the way of treaty: this hath been acted both by writings and conference: <hi>Sancta Clara</hi> himselfe saith, <hi>Doctissimi eorum quibus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque egi:</hi> so it seems they have had conference together: and <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta Clara</hi> on his part labours to bring the Articles of our Church to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and some of our side labour to meet him in the way: we have a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony that the great Arch-Priest himselfe hath said, <hi>It were no hard matter to make a reconciliation if a wise man had the handling of it.</hi> But I verily believe, as the state of Papacy stands, a farre wiser man then he cannot reconcile us without the losse of our Religion: for the Pope being fastened to his errours, even by his chaire of inerrability, he sits still unmoved, and so we cannot meet, except we come wholly to him. A man standing in a boat tied to a rock, when he drawes the rope, doth not draw the rock to the boat, but the boat to the rock. And <hi>Sancta Clara</hi> doth (in this somewhat honestly) confesse it: for he saith he dealt in this way of treaty, not to draw the Church to the Protestants, but the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants to the Church.</p>
            <p>A third way is a way of violence: this violence they exercise, partly by secular Arms, and partly by Priestly Armes, which they call spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: for secular armes, we have their own confession, that the late warre was <hi>Bellum Episcopale:</hi> and we have the Papists confession, that it was <hi>Bellum Papale:</hi> for in their motives they say, that the warre concernes them not only as subjects, but as Catholikes: for so they falsly call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25:9"/>and if it be so, then <hi>bellum episcopale</hi> is also <hi>bellum pap<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the Episcopall warre the Papall cause is advanced: for the spirituall Armes, thus they come to execution. When a great man is coming, h<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> sumpters, his furniture, his provisions go before: the Popes furnit<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, Altars and Copes, Pictures and Images are come before: and if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve D. <hi>Cosin,</hi> the very substance of the Masse: a certain signe the the Pope was not farre off. Now these fore-runners being come, if any man resist them, fire comes out of the brambles, and devoures the Cedars of Libanus: the Army of Priests fals upon him with their armes of Suspention, Sequestration, Excommunication, Degradation and Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. And by these armes hath <hi>M. Smart</hi> been oppressed and undone, he fals upon their superstitions and innovations, and they fall upon him with their armes: they beat him down, yea they pull him up by the roots, taking away all his means of maintenance and living, yet they leave him life to feel his miseries: <hi>Ita feriunt ut diu se sentiat mori,</hi> there is no cruelty to priestly cruelty: these are they that did put our very Saviour to death: the calling is reverend, but the corruption is most pernicious: <hi>Corruptio optimi peffima:</hi> I know no reason of this change, except it be that of the Apostle, because when they knew God, they did not worship him as God, but made a god of this world, placing the excellency of Priesthood in worldly pomp and greatnesse: and gave the glory of the invisible God to pictures, images and altars: therefore God gave them up to vile affections, to be implacable, unmercifull, and without naturall affection. But whatsoever the cause is of their corruption, certainly their armes have fallen heavy upon <hi>M. Smart,</hi> and priestly cruelty hath cast him into a long misery, from which he could get no release by any priestly mercy.</p>
            <p>And now it is prayed, that as these delinquents by the cruell oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of <hi>M. Smart</hi> have advanced the cause of Popery, so they may in such a degree of justice be punished, that in them priestly cruelty, and the very cause of Popery may appeare to be punished and suppressed: And that <hi>M. Smart,</hi> suffering for the cause of Protestancy, may be so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, that in him pious constancy, and the very cause of Protest<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> may appeare to be righted and repaired.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>